<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Jetty6</title>
  </properties>
  <head>
     <META http-equiv="Cache-Control" content="no-cache,no-store"/>
  </head>
  <body>
<div class="summary">
<span>Jetty 6</span> is the newest version of Jetty and supports the new 2.5 version of the Servlet Specification. 
<P>
Our goal with Jetty 6 was not just to bolt-on support for 2.5, but to take the opportunity to assess the codebase and re-architect and re-implement where necessary to make Jetty as streamlined and efficient as possible without sacrificing features and functionality.
</P>
<P>
A number of other changes were introduced and improvements made in jetty 6:
</P>

<h2>Embeddability</h2>
<p>
As a result of paring down the dependencies and careful design, jetty 6 can deliver a webserver with just 3 jars:  servlet-api-2.5.jar, jetty.jar and jetty-util.jar. We're also vigilant about keeping the size of those jars to the minimum necessary.
</p>

<h2>Scalability</h2>
<P>
One of our big motivators was to address scalability, which has become particularly important with the popularity of 
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AJAX">AJAX</a>. In the AJAX model, web browser clients
continuously poll the server. The server will often delay processing the request until there is data to 
send or a timeout happens. That means that the server processing thread and resources are being held open for relatively long periods, which is disastrous for heavily loaded sites. Jetty 6 address this by offering a feature called <a href="/apidocs/org/mortbay/util/ajax/package-summary.html">Continuations</a>, which allows a request to be suspended (and therefore the server resources freed) and resumed later.
</P>
<h2>Efficiency</h2>
<P>
We've also improved efficiency by adding connectors based on Sun's non-blocking IO 
<a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/api/java/nio/channels/package-summary.html">(NIO)</a> package. We've also re-designed the buffering to take advantage of NIO, and also to make flushing as efficient as possbile.
</P>
</div>

Here's a summary of the new features of jetty6:
<div class="feature">
<div class="featureitem">Codebase completely rearchitected and slimlined</div>
<div class="featureitem"><a href="/apidocs/org/mortbay/util/ajax/package-summary.html">Continuations API</a> for efficient AJAX polling</div>
<div class="featureitem">Improved dependancy injection and inversion of control design of components</div>
<div class="featureitem">Improved interceptor design of handlers</div>
<div class="featureitem">Smart split buffer design for efficient asynchronous flushing and avoiding chunking.</div>
<div class="featureitem">Optional use of NIO Buffering so that efficient direct buffers and memory mapped files can be used.</div>
<div class="featureitem">Optional use of NIO non-blocking scheduling so that threads are not allocated per connection.</div>
<div class="featureitem">Optional use of NIO gather writes, so that for example a HTTP header and a memory mapped file may be sent as a single operation.</div>
</div>

  </body>
</document>
