<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>jetty6 WebServer</title>
    <head>
     <META http-equiv="Cache-Control" content="no-cache,no-store"/>
    </head>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section>
     <div class="study">
       <img src="http://jetty.mortbay.org/jetty/images/casestudy.gif" />
       <h2><a href="http://www.mortbay.com/MB/log/gregw/?permalink=ScalingConnections.html">Scaling Connections for AJAX with Jetty 6</a></h2>
       <div>
Jetty 6 employs a number of innovative strategies to ensure that only the resources that are actually required are assigned to a connection and only for the duration of they are needed. This careful resource management gives Jetty an architecture designed to scale to meet the needs of AJAX applications.
      </div>
       <a href="http://www.mortbay.com/MB/log/gregw/?permalink=ScalingConnections.html">Read more ...</a>
    </div>
<div class="siteheader">
jetty6 
</div>

<div class="summary">
<span>jetty6</span> is a new implementation of the popular 
<a href="http://jetty.mortbay.org/jetty">Jetty</a> HTTP Server and Servlet Container.  
The idea behind jetty6 is to build on over 10 years experience creating and maintaining
Jetty to produce a new container. With jetty6, we've concentrated
on keeping the footprint to a minimum by reducing the dependencies on 3rd party libraries and
by being rigorous with clean code, making it even easier to embed Jetty.

<P>Our other paramount concerns are efficiency and scalability. For example, jetty6 comes with the same set of 
connector types as standard Jetty, but also now includes connectors based on Sun's non-blocking IO 
<a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/api/java/nio/channels/package-summary.html">(NIO)</a> package.
</P>
<P>
Scalability is a particlarly important concern with the advent of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AJAX">AJAX</a>. In the AJAX model, clients
continuously poll the server, which often delays processing the request until there is data to 
send or a timeout happens. This means that server threads are being held open leading to scalability
problems for heavily loaded sites. jetty6's response is to offer a feature called <a href="/jetty6/jetty/apidocs/org/mortbay/util/ajax/package-summary.html">Continuations</a>
allowing a request to be suspended (and therefore the thread freed) and resumed later.
</P>
Here's a summary of the new features of jetty6:
<div class="feature">
<div class="featureitem">Codebase completely rearchitected and slimlined</div>
<div class="featureitem"><a href="/jetty6/jetty/apidocs/org/mortbay/util/ajax/package-summary.html">Continuations API</a> for efficient AJAX polling</div>
<div class="featureitem">Improved dependancy injection and inversion of control design of components</div>
<div class="featureitem">Improved interceptor design of handlers</div>
<div class="featureitem">Smart split buffer design for efficient asynchronous flushing and avoiding chunking.</div>
<div class="featureitem">Optional use of NIO Buffering so that efficient direct buffers and memory mapped files can be used.</div>
<div class="featureitem">Optional use of NIO non-blocking scheduling so that threads are not allocated per connection.</div>
<div class="featureitem">Optional use of NIO gather writes, so that for example a HTTP header and a memory mapped file may be sent as a single operation.</div>
</div>
</div>


  </section>
  </body>
</document>
